hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights as always I'm
your host darus parvey Wayne and today I
have the great pleasure of speaking to
Mr although very soon it will be Dr
Lance D Costa Lance is a PhD student
with Greg pavus and KL friston jointly
at Imperial College London in UCL and
his work lies at the intersection of
mathematics cognitive science and
machine learning indeed he is at the
very Cutting Edge of the technical
formulations underlying AC of inference
and so I'm personally looking forward to
learning from him today and I hope you
are too ladies and gentlemen I bring you
Lance the Costa Lance thank you so much
I I genuinely meant what I don't really
like doing the introduction because it
feels so you know sort of a bit stagnant
and rigid but I genuinely meant what I
wrote there which is that I'm really
looking forward to learning than for
having me and appreciate the
introduction yeah um and you will when
when is when is one when do you expect
to become a doctor when's that total
happening so my defense is at the end of
February so oh my gosh it's inth yeah
wow fingers crossed I'm sure you'll
smash it thanks so before we start
getting into the maths I this is very
exciting for me because you're the first
I would say pretty much pure
mathematician we've had on we've had
computer scientists we've had cognitive
scientists but no one really uh delving
into the the nether regions of the maths
um you know when I was researching what
you're interested in I came across um
the fact that you're interested in World
models and I'm also very interested in
World models so I wanted to start there
as's like a teaser before we get into
the maths and I wanted to ask whether
you could explain what you mean by a
world model and how you distinguish that
from a self model and the reason why I
ask that question is kind of twofold one
is that I think the word world models
might be slightly misleading because it
kind of implies that we're modeling the
world and in some sense we are but we're
definitely not modeling the entire world
so it might be called something like an
econ Niche
model yeah although that's less catchy
and then the other reason is I think
there's still an open question at least
to my eyes in active inference about
whether we are modeling the world and
ourselves or whether we're just modeling
the world and we fit into that in some
way right so it would be great to unpick
that if possible yeah that that's
actually a Cutting Edge question but I
really like it great so let me start by
world
what I mean what I personally mean by
World model is that you as an individual
you have always some sensory data coming
in off active Visual auditive and so
forth and you're going to build a model
for what's going on outside that causes
your data um now the model that you
build is a generative model which means
that you can generate kind of factual
data about what might happen in the
future what might happen if I do this
and that uh it's a probalistic model
because you're always uncertain about
what's going on around in the world and
it's also a causal model um this means
that you're not um you're not exploiting
the well you're not exploiting just the
correlations in the data that come in
but you're actually explaining the
causes of the data something like more
powerful than than a statistical
model uh now I think you're right in
calling it an eon Niche model because I
mean the data that we have coming in at
any point in time is just from around us
and so that's ultimately what we want to
model uh when we talk about the free
energy principle we say that the brain
optimizes its model to maximize accuracy
and minimize
complexity um in that and and that
entails uh having a model that's as
simple as possible and therefore you
don't want a model things are like too
far away from you important from you and
so this is why having an eon model as a
terminology makes more sense sure so
when you talked about world model and
self model and this is where it really
gets Cutting Edge uh so in the like
simple applications of active inference
and AI you just care about modeling the
world um but now as humans we don't only
do that so for instance if I take a
particular if I make a particular
decision or take a particular course of
action and you ask me why did you do
that I'm not going to be able to uh
answer in saying oh this neuron did this
and this neuron did that and this
happened but I'm going to give you a
high level overview using natural
language of why I did this now this uh
is the idea of
metacognition which means of having a
model of the self in addition of having
a model of the world so you have a model
of yourself and you have a model of your
own cognition and so this is kind of
like a higher form of cognition and
active inference uh which has not so far
been really implemented out there I
believe at least in machine learning
it's kind of come out in papers on um
modeling meditation with active
inference L's work yeah I like yeah yeah
yeah very nice cool that's really so so
you so this is yeah this is a question
I've been entertaining when I wrote this
first paper on Flow that I've now
mentioned far too many times so I shall
mention it again um I was thinking
exactly what are we talking about when
we're talking about something like an
epistemic agent model and uh I remember
one comment commentator said oh is it
just
metacognition so that's an interesting
alignment there um because in a sense
yes you're right we have to reflect on
our own capacities and model that as an
inference my only question there is you
know in L's paper you have these really
beautiful hierarchical Baye
graphs do you think there's a there has
to be an upper bound on the
computational complexity of that
metacognitive and what and is is that
just a limitation of the computation in
and of itself or does it mean that there
might be something ontologically sort of
actually there right what what do you
mean by ontological exactly uh let's
well let's let's use a word well I'm not
going to invoke something like a
Cartesian soul but is there any I guess
is there anything unique beyond the
algorithm beyond the probabilistic model
right uh so what I would say to that I
mean what we're personally investigating
with Lars is what does metacognition
actually allow us to do allow us to do
that's uh you know important for
survival that an agent that does not
have metacognition is not able to do so
the idea is if metacognition arose at
some point is because it increases our
chances of survival our fitness it
minimizes our free energy um how exactly
I mean how is metacognition useful
beyond what you know what we just talked
about uh is currently unknown at least
for me sure yeah I think it's I think
it's a complex issue because it it's
entangled with common folk psychology
Notions of what it is to be a self um so
most people will think of themselves uh
probably if you ask them they would say
yes I am this substantial thing somewhat
behind my eyes uh that persist through
time so somewhat of some kind of
cartisian rified ego and I actually
found I I find that active influence is
a lot easier to pass once we take that
out of the equation when you just have
the physics or when you just have the
statistical mechanics it becomes a lot
easier to say okay maybe this is maybe
the self is just a further inference
that's kind of where I was pushing you
in terms of the ontological thing
because I think people listening if they
haven't really you know thought about
the the Buddhism and the metacognition
and the Derek parit related philosophy
might think well there's just something
there that's doing it right there's
something there that's a homunculus
behind the eyes that's actually doing
the calculations that's doing the
variational basing inference but I
assume you can't you know there's no
notion of that in your
models um so you mean like kind of like
a an agent inside the agent indeed and
obviously this leads to a homuncular
infinite regress because who's watching
the screen and so you know and so on but
I think people have an issue with just a
raw notion that there's just algorithmic
computation going on because they're
going to ask well who wait what who is
doing it and that leads us back to some
kind of uh active agent that's actually
there not just an emergent
phenomenon right uh so so I have a few
things to say about that I think uh so
when we when we engage in meditation we
are computationally looks like we're
building a higher level in our giant
model which is kind of like another age
inside that makes inferences about our
cognition yes and so when you're a
trained meditator you not only think
about the world or experience the world
but you experience your own cognitive
processes and you train yourself in
doing that now how that looks like
computationally is that you have a
hierarchical gen model with many levels
of of abstraction but when you translate
that into math and physics it's kind of
this idea of the Russian do yes like an
outside agent and some more like more
agents inside hierarch stacked that just
infer each other
yes Mark of blanket in some sense yeah
nested Mark of blankets and so but that
but you know that analogy implies that
there is some outer
shell that might be right only that
might be you know yeah this makes me
think of Maxwell Ramsey the M's paper on
Consciousness that there's this right
only layer that is contextualizing but
not
contextualized um but that's kind of the
other way around right that's like
that's the that's kind of like the prime
mover unmoved whereas your I feel like
your argument is saying well everything
is contextualizing everything else and
actually what we might call the AL shell
the autobiographical self is just the
aggregation of all of these other selves
does that sound about right yeah it I
feel it's uh kind of hard for me to to
describe it um and I'm also thinking
along these lines but I would say I mean
the freeer principle everything is
dependent on the blanket that you select
right and is the idea that we have
multiple nested blankets now the story
that you tell depend on which blanket
you decide to talk
about do you I think people have an
intuitive folk psychology notion that of
course there's a point at which the
modeling of me as a discrete identity
needs to stop St so we could keep Mo so
so most people probably think about the
surface of the skin the epithelium and
say well that that that's me right and
then we can get into conversations about
extended mind hypothesis but I actually
don't think it's that relevant here I
guess the point is
um it seems like that the point at which
we stop the mark of blanket is actually
it's not arbitrary but it's an open
question it's philosophically vague so
to speak um which which which negates
the kind of folk psychology notion that
there is something like me which has
these strict
bounds yeah so so I I completely agree
with kind of like the disolution of
those straight bounds once you start
looking at it very carefully intuitively
I think that my you know my hands are
mine because I can control them in a
relatively precise way and I think this
is where that comes from okay it is the
preciseness at which you can act on
something or
inert that's nice
yeah when you when you do a lot of
meditation or when you when you look at
it like very carefully you start
realizing that there's so many things in
your body that you cannot control it's
kind of obvious when when you think
about it and you start realizing that
you have very little agency over many
things that are happening in your body
so I think everyone of us has things
that they're satisfied and they
satisfied about themselves when you
think about it where maybe I'm
dissatisfied with something about
myself uh but then this is not really my
fault of me being that way so here's an
example of um of something that I cannot
control once you reflect that on that
more and more you start realizing that
you know uh we are self-organizing
systems just like a tornado is a
self-organizing system and we have a lot
of things that are going on inside our
bodies inside our minds that you cannot
just cannot control H so yeah that's
interesting I
guess I guess my rebuttal to that would
be arguably the literature says that or
suggests there are processes that
underly something like a uh minimal self
like inter receptive inference so that
can be done reflexively or through kind
of alistic control so let's say my
glucose level drops Beyond a certain
level I either you know secrete the
necessary hormones or go out there and
eat but let's just say I'm secreting
those hormones I'm not act you know my
autobiographical self doesn't have the
doesn't have the sense it's doing
anything yeah th that mechanism of
prediction Eros suppression is
supposedly at the heart of the sense of
mindness and
presence so how do we resolve that if
we're casting selfhood as that which is
within my
control um well I I don't know to be
honest
but it's a it's a a difficult question
but
uh yeah I mean the the more the more I
think about all of this and the more I
read the more I realize that we have
control over very little yeah
and so in in the meditation books so I
keep coming to that because they're a
source of inspiration for me for
describing high level cognition there is
this um like fundamental truth qu quote
unquote which that there is no self the
more you start like investigating the
Mind through self inquiry the more you
realize that there is no self yeah yeah
um so maybe it speaks kind of to the
things that we're just discussing sure
yes this is yeah this is an interesting
point um I guess you one would have to
ask very dedicated meditators uh whether
when they're doing let's say Vasa and
they break that kind of Duality um
because you know the subject OB object
duality yielding to Oneness is kind of a
seminal phenomenon that occurs whether
that sense of mindness and presence is
also lost so there's an you know uh John
vvi who's one of my favorite cognitive
scientists and who was on the podcast
speaks about adverbial qualia and what
he means by that is you there are these
so-called pure Consciousness events and
even in those the sense of presence and
perhaps mindness although we kind of
weren't sure um might still be present
which I which to my ears sounds like
some computational mechanism like
interceptive inference still being at
play so I I guess this is calling
for calling for a denial of the strict
distinction between the body and the
mind that the interceptive inference can
still underly or bodily inference can
still underly very important
phenomenology yeah well uh active
inference is definitely taking this uh
philosophical position that cognition is
embodied so so yeah it speaks exactly to
what you said now I I just want to add
something else so we talked about the
the model of the self and I would say
there's actually two models of the self
so there's the model of the body and and
this has a like clear um evolutionary
like reason for being there so for
example if something in my body hurts I
need to figure out what to do about it
for it not to hurt so it's about
preserving your homeostasis and
fulfilling preferences now there's this
other level that we've also been
discussing which is like the model of
our own cognition these are two
different things yes that's that's
interesting yeah cool there's lots
there's lots to chew on there I'm glad
that I'm glad that this is Cutting Edge
questions that need Cutting Edge these
are really things uh that I know a lot
of people are thinking about spended
yeah I think I think I'm gonna I'm gonna
have lws on at some point
yeah he owes me that to be honest uh he
keeps promising okay um let's to the bet
you know this is this self-modeling
philosophical conversation is more my
bag but let's take that deep PL uh
plunge into the mathematics so as a as a
kind of a forewarning or a precursory
warning to the audience I'm not a
mathematician um so everything I'm doing
when I'm reading the math I'm trying to
ground in intuitive philosophically
robust Concepts so just just for the
audience and yourself please do excuse
me if I [ __ ] up um you won't I mean this
is a I think it's very important to be
able to talk about these things without
the
math it's literally impossible to talk
in math so yes yeah yeah yeah there's
this about this in a in a natural
language way that's hopefully as simple
as possible please well yeah I guess
that's how it has to be taught is
through metaphor um sort of yeah life
through metaphor for George Lov kind of
stuff so um start starting right at the
basis in Act of inference the world is
described as a random dynamical
system defined or described by a
stochastic differential equation like a
leran equation yeah why why is it
worthwhile starting there why is that
the starting point right um should
should I explain briefly what Lan
equation is perhaps sure it'll be better
you doing it than me okay uh sure well
um so here's the thing we want a
fundamental theory of the brain and
cognition and we want it to be grounded
in math and
physics um now if you look at the
fundamental theories that exist in
physics these would be uh general
relativity classical mechanics
statistical mechanics quantum physics
they are all based on stochastic
differential equations or long my
equations at some level now um a
stochastic differential equation is a
very fundamental and also basic object
and I'll explain why it's basic it's
basic in the sense that when you're
modeling a system there are the known
knowns and they're the known unknowns
yeah stochastic differential equation uh
brings the two together so there may be
the known knowns about the system which
could be forces that act on different
components of the system this is going
to drive the system deterministically
along a predetermined path and then
there are known unknowns these could be
random fluctuations for example if you
have a drone this could be random
fluctuations due to wind if you have a
boat random fluctuations due to waves
and these are things that you possibly
cannot accurately
capture so you're going to summarize
them in a random
term and then together so you have this
deterministic uh term that gives you a
predetermined traj and you have this
random term that sort of perturbs the
trajectory in a random way and when you
put the two together you get kind of
like a random evolution of your system
with some structure and this is
basically what the Lan equation or
stochastic differential equation um
encodes so this is to say uh it's a very
general starting point and it's also the
starting point that's consistent with
the rest of physics and that's why we
start there when we uh when we think
about the free principle
excellent yeah so there's a couple
things I wanted to pick up um am I right
to say that it's about the rate of
change of so of some X let's say of some
states is that is that so that's that's
kind of what we're looking at here is
the okay and then the second thing is um
this notion of random
noise if you speak to certain
philosophers for example they might say
well it depends on who you ask I guess
um because for a universal you know for
um for some Demon that knows the entire
unfoldings of the world in a single
glance there's no Randomness true and
yet to us the modelers well it's just
computationally impossible to know every
single element of the wind let's say or
the waves so what what are we talking
about are we talking about Rand
Randomness in in and of itself in the
actual system that's being modeled or
for the
modular this is a great question uh so
here it's it's agnostic in the sense
that uh you could imagine you could
model the the the system that you're
trying to model in all in explicit
detail so that you know absolutely
everything that's going on in that case
you would have no
Randomness in that case you still have a
stochastic differential equation with no
stochastic term which is an ordinary
differential equation but still atic
differential equation so the same math
apply sure you just have a random term
that's like zero yeah yeah yeah maybe
there are things that you cannot model
accurately in the system so you put them
in some noise and the same math
applies so I would say it's noise from
the perspective of the modeler or not
and and we don't actually care the point
is that once you start from the
assumption that you can model the system
in that way then then things carry
through and I make the presump I I'm
presuming here that that noise is G is
is considered gussan it's consider a
normal distribution gem yeah so
generally for uh for for you to be able
to do mathematics you take G
noise is that an
issue well it depends on who you ask
like uh most math and physics is based
on gaussian noise because it represents
the mo the world most accurately you
have something called the central limit
theorem that if you have a lot of like
fluctuations they kind of average away
in a pile of sand yeah yeah so your
noise turns out to be often times very
well approximated by by gaussian process
uh but then there there are instances
where gaussian noise is not accurate so
for example if you're talking to people
who model the financial Market they do
not use gin noise they use noise with
like jumps to model like a very sharp um
yeah jumps in the
market so ga noise is a good place to
start I think ultimately as we work on
the free engine principle mathematically
we want to be much more inclusive sure
isn't that I mean just as a side isn't
that a remarkable fact that like
stochastic processes tend towards B Gan
it's just like yeah I think it's awesome
it's amazing yeah yeah I mean you have
all these remarkable properties of the G
distribution um and it's also like the
only one distribution that we actually
know how to work with very well so it's
a good thing yeah it's cool um and then
I guess my other question about the
leran equation is you have sort of f ofx
as the deterministic force so it's a
function of the states of X the flow of
X is that right yeah right yeah but I
that doesn't have a kind of comma T next
to it um why is that not uh a function
of time as well so it it could be in in
its most general form F the flow would
be also a function of time now if you
think of it let's say you have a state
space and you have time you can just
incorporate time as another element as
another state so you consider your state
space to be space time and then you're
back at F ofx right so I think that's
why that's why often times people just
go with f of x cool okay excellent now
let's jump to the next step we have
density Dynamics and the fuer plank
equation and the path integral
formulation right very fundamental
question what is the difference between
those two there there's no difference
there's just different ways of
articulating the same thing okay so the
L of equation gives you like the rate of
change
as a function of the flow and a random
component random noise yeah uh then when
you sort of solve that you you sort of
get um this is the probability that the
system T takes this trajectory and this
is the probability that gets this other
trajectory and so
forth this information is what's carried
in the path integral formulation the
path integral formulation gives you the
negative log probability of a path y
and then you the focal plank
equation uh which says at any point in
time this is the distribution that
enclos the system so you might in a
predefined place that you know I mean
the system might be might start in a
particular location in safe space m
because of the flow and the random
fluctuations uh at time t+ one the
system will be it could be here it could
be there it could be there with a
different probability and then there's a
prob distribution that summarizes this
and this is what's incuding the focal
plank equation FOC plank they both come
to the same conclusion you run the maths
both ways and they all converge the
answer that it's it's exactly the same
thing yeah it's like different ways of
looking at the same thing and depending
on the question that you want to answer
uh taking one formalism or another is
easier but the point is that you can
always go from one to the other and back
nice okay that's cool um okay let's jump
into the fu plank equation because I've
been I've been doing some reading and I
might be wrong but I'm excited about it
it's excited me so cool yeah so from
what I've learned it's a partial
differential equation yeah that rate
that relates the rate of change of the
probability density function so that's
that P with the little Dot and X comma
t with respect to time drift and
diffusion right how's that sounding
yeah it's a great
summary I can elaborate on that a little
bit to please well people have no idea
what I'm talking about so okay well
you'll see that you got it perfectly
right oh thank God for that all right
please explain in a l equation you have
the rate of change of the state y the
flow and the random term yes um now this
is what physicist called it but if you
talk to mathematician he would say you
have the rate of change of state States
the drift and a random term which they
call the diffusion yes nice or which is
characterized by the diffusion so then
the focal plank equation is very similar
you have instead of having the rate of
change of the state you have the rate of
change of the probability density that
describes the state and then this is
given as a function of the drift so the
flow and the diffusion so the random
term Okay cool so so um if we were going
to cast this in like in terms of just
cartisian coordinates just X and Y axis
would it be right to say that we could
have X as like the position let's say of
because I I read there's a lot here in
sort of brownan particles so let say I
had my particles in some you know doing
brownan motion the X would be the
position of some particle and the Y
would be the probability of finding it
there yeah when you talk about the focal
plank equation yes yeah so the focal
plank equation would would be that so at
each point in time the the solution to
the focal plank equation is the density
of the system that evolves over time and
so you could plot this on the XY axis as
you said on the x axis you would have
the position of the system on the y axis
you would have the probability
probability distribution and so if we
imagine things are simple so if we
imagine the system is always gaussian
distrib according to gaussin
distribution then if you solve the FOC
plank equation you would have a gaussin
that Evol over time Su the mean would be
shifting and the variance would be
shifting also potentially nice okay cool
that's that's really useful so how would
we then integrate time is it is it this
like is is the is that X and Y AIS
considered like a snapshot in time yeah
okay excellent yes okay cool that's
actually really useful because I think
people might got confused by that um
yeah now let's get to so this gives us
density
Dynamics but when we talk about active
we about we talk about steady state
densities right so people I think have
this intuitive notion from whether
they're coming from dynamical systems
theory or something else of a kind of
basin right in ATT tractor set I mean I
think of it kind of like a magnet um
just
metaphorically what is how do we get
from density Dynamics to a steady state
density um so I should cave at this by
saying that the latest formulations of
the free energy principle are not based
on having a steady state density
that's like a new thing and I think for
like intuition it's best to think about
the steady state case okay
so um kind of like the intuition is that
if you're modeling an agent uh it has a
preferred set of states that it likes to
come back to or that it like does
everything it can to like be back at
those States you could think of like
homeostatic States for
instance um you can also think about the
fact that if you're modeling A system
that does not dissipate in time so let's
say like not a gas for
instance uh then the system should also
have like a steady state at least over a
short period of time because it doesn't
dissipate right so now we're going to
try to
model um I mean the free principle is
about modeling or analyzing those
systems that have a steady state that
have these sort of preferred set of
states and so you ask if a system has a
preferred set of States and it's also
decomposed into an organism its boundary
and what's not the organism again this
could be like a living organism it could
be a stone it could be anything that has
a
boundary uh then you basically look at
what the internal states do what do this
what does the boundary States uh do how
do they evolve and what do the external
states do and then the conclusion is
that in general the internal States look
as if I mean I mean they they're you can
describe them as inferring the external
States based blanket States yeah yeah
yeah yes that's an interesting
formulation and one we could come back
to which is this kind of uh yeah
tracking in some variational Basi and
inference way um we've spoken about this
sort of looking like very important two
words in the free energy principle um a
number of times in this in this podcast
but I was curious more about in terms of
the fuer plank equation I don't know why
I've turned into a
um so so this is the way that I would
think about and please feel free to from
what I've learned very you know in a
very shallow way is that we had this um
this probability density function so
let's say as you say we have our X we
have our position y we have our
probability distribution let's just say
it's gussan and per attractor State per
organism per attractor State it's going
to be different right so mine might be
really close to this size yours whatever
um what what I kind of understood as a
steady state is over time so let's say
now we like put all of those images of
the X and Y axis on top of each other
right right and let's say they were
somewhat
translucent you wouldn't if it's steady
state you expect that probability
distribution to like stay on top of
itself if it's not you'll expect it to
shift from side to
side yeah or or like become completely
flat all okay all become completely flat
I guess reincarnation would be kind of
gaussian flat
gaussian what what do you mean by
reincarnation sorry well let's say I it
was it was a tongue and- cheek comment
but let like I have a gaussian
distribution of being in a certain state
right right right I die I enter into the
EPA I dissolve into the heat I flatten
out and then I reappear as a frog and I
enter into a new galaxian distribution
yeah that's a good way to put it all
right nice okay so is that is that does
how does that sound mathematically what
does that look like mathematically okay
so um I think one yeah I think there's
kind of like two
scenarios uh
one one is that there's no steady state
and the system
dissipates um and therefore you're
you're like snapshots of uh of the like
the density at each point in time will
converge to a flat distribution
okay um and and the other case is that
there is a steady state and uh the
snapshots converge onto like a a clear
well defined distribution yeah which be
like a gaussian or something else and
the is that the point the point of a
steady state is uh that if you start the
system in that distribution it will
remain in that distribution sure
although okay okay fine and and that's
strict as in you will stay within that
distribution or is there permission
let's say in sentient creatures like our
own for that distribution to change
somewhat um so that's a good question uh
there's kind of like two answers to
that you being at a pre-specified
distribution does not mean that you're
not doing interesting things yeah so if
we just think about a convection
cell you basically like or or a tornado
you have like this circling
around uh the probability distribution
of where the gas is or where the turning
is just stays constant it's kind of like
this ring shape uh but you still have
some interesting motion
inside um right so I might not
always doesn't
me right because I might just you know
over time it will look like I'm
converging on that state but I might not
always be
there yeah your probability it's kind of
like hard to wrap your
heads um if you think about like
homeostasis right if you model if you
like let's say temperature if you model
temperature you can imagine it would
have a gussian distribution sort of with
the Peak at 37.9 degrees Centigrade
let's say but you are not going to spend
your entire life at 37.9 degrees
Centigrade exactly you're going to move
around and on will be according to this
Gan distribution right right okay cool
um okay good um I I want to jump to that
notion of the internal States tracking
the external States cuz I think people
struggle with that um and I definitely
did for a while so so the way that I
read internal and external is tracking
and tracked um that for me has been a
really parsimonious and useful way I
think I got that from Maxwell that
that's a really nice way of thinking
about it because the internal external
is such a philosophically Troublesome
distinction so tracking and track and
then I think of something like the
equation variational free
energy and I think about the KO
Divergence between the recognition
density and the true posterior and the
maximization of model
evidence now in
that I guess I'm not I don't have to
necessarily make this strict distinction
between the internal States my States
and the worldly States because all I'm
doing there is I'm saying I have you
know give uh given some observation I
have a probability distribution of some
State whether they're mine or whether
they're the world's because for me I'm
not going for me there that distinction
is not that strong because for me I
think you could pose that actually all
that we are are just this aggregation of
worldly States right I am just I am one
temperature distribution I am one
glucose distribution that's not mine
that's the
world's yeah um so so that's the first
thing right so we're doing this x uh X
give and Y this recognition density
and then you have the maximization of
the model evidence which is the
probability of why given your
model but again there's nothing like
internal that's going on there it's just
statistics so do you that do do do you
think that it's somewhat Troublesome to
cast like put this little homunculus or
this little ego in the internal States
and being like he's doing sufficient
statistics is that do you see that
slightly
Troublesome um I think it's a nice
picture for ination but it's
certainly uh it can be misleading for
the reasons that you pointed out uh
internal and external States can be
interchanged yeah and again it's all
about the blanket yeah the exter the
external States could be part of your
own body and the internal States could
be part of your brain and the blanket
somewhere in between or the internal
States could be like a school of fish
and the external States could be like a
predator right um yeah I just never
thought I this is no attack on anyone I
don't know who came up with it probably
KL sorry KL I never thought that was a
particularly good formulation of the
free energy principle I always thought
that um you know things that seem to
persist look like they're maximizing
model evidence for themselves is way
better um but this is something to take
out with him yeah but but it's kind of
like two things we're touching on here
because tracking and the Mel
evidence uh they kind of like two things
are going
on because when you think about it the
free energy is this K Divergence plus
the
surprise uh and we use this tracking to
like minimize the free energy right so
what I mean by that is the maximization
of model evidence or I think it's the
minimization of log model evidence but
it's the same thing
um that entails that in of itself what
the way I'm trying to frame it is that
that entails some form of tracking yeah
because you've got that you got that
probability of why but it's sort of
given your
model um so yeah I I just think for
people this is again this more an
education point about active inference
not about the maths or anything um I
just sense that for me it's always been
more intuitive to think about that
although again it's hardly intuitive is
it I mean it takes a bit of time to
really wrap your head around yeah
there's there's another important point
that came out in the research uh when we
are talking about the fact that you can
I mean a lot of people say that you can
always interchange uh internal and
external States and that one is tracking
and the other is tracked but it turns
out that this is not always the case
because for the internal states to track
the external States they need to have
enough like representational
capacity make inferences about all the
internal states are out there they don't
have enough representational capacity
maybe they might just infer some or
infer linear combinations of external
States in any case they're just going to
have like part of the
picture okay that's no that's that's
interesting which means that for
external states to track internal States
they also need to have like enough
representational capacity and a
sufficiently high quality coupling with
their own sensory states with the
boundary to make inferences about the
internal States so you always have this
synchronization and this inference going
on you Cann necessarily say that the
internal States will be tracking all the
internal States all the time or or vice
versa right kind of depends on the
Integrity of the coupling and how much
representational capacity these states
have well again that's why for me this
maximization of model evidence just
seems a little bit simpler because
whether you're a drop of oil or a rock
or human
we can sort of arbit you know not
arbitrarily but we can generously give
out models for each one of them and say
that they look like they're maximizing
mod evidence yeah now um like how long
something lasts is a different question
um so my you know the the the salt that
I put in water maximizes model evidence
for itself being so for a very short
amount of time so you know you could
cast that as it surprise will being very
high but at least for while it's salt
it's maximizing model evidence and then
I guess it's maximizing model evidence
within a Markov blanket that's the water
salt solution anyway it's an interesting
foray but it's no that's a good point
yeah we're now going to jump to the next
part of this so people who want to
follow along by the way a lot of this is
from the free energy principle made
simple but not too simple or I think
that's the name of the title that's
right yeah that's a great this this is a
well I wouldn't say it's necessarily
a perfect starting point for someone who
hasn't done maths or physics don't we I
would I would recommend um the
textbook so paret Zulo and friston you
got recommendations actually yeah
there's also Maxwell's paper on Basin
mechanics yeah that's very good and off
beliefs and this is really cutting edge
in describing the math but it's also
meant to be much more
approachable yes okay that's yep so
Maxwell's 2023 paper which is on the uh
pre-print server um the textbook and
I've also been reading and we'll come to
this I've been reading sanjie Nam josi's
draft of his p uh book it's it's it's
being sort of distributed there's a
group in the active inference Institute
where you can read it and that's been
really useful so there's stuff out there
and and there podcast
and so yeah but if you wanted to follow
along with this this is that uh B uh
free energy principle made simpler but
not too simple so the next thing that
you you come to there is solenoidal and
gradient
flows right so maybe we can talk about
maybe we should start by just explaining
what those two flows mean and how
they're distinct from one
another okay um so this is a the
composition of the flow in the Lan
equation yeah and
so uh to put it simp to put it very
simply
the um well just to give an analogy in
Vector calculus you have this
fundamental theorem about that's known
as the hamle dec composition yeah which
says that if you have a vector field so
think about a bunch of vectors sitting
on a
table uh you can decompose them onto uh
one that's kind of like circling around
an origin to put it simply and one
that's going inside or outside okay so
mathematically this is what we're doing
here to decompose uh the flow in the L
equation now what this really means in
practice is that you have uh the
solenoidal flow which is the interesting
part of the flow and the how did you
call the other one uh what did I call it
gradient flow right and there's a
gradient flow that's the in
uninteresting one if you are um if you
are a living system you have by
definition solenoidal flow and why is
that solenoidal flow is is um related to
time irreversibility and entropy
production um okay if if you don't have
solenoidal flow it means that the system
if you if you play it in time uh as time
goes forward and then you you reverse
the movie statistically the system will
look the same so it's essentially a dead
system it could be like a stone for
instance yeah on the other hand if I you
know you play the podcast for 20 seconds
as time goes forward and then you play
it backward for 20 seconds it will look
super weird and very different right
this is the proof that there is time
irreversibility time has a there is a
direction time um and this is yeah
characteristic of the fact that we are
alive interesting okay so let me just
get some some more you know some simple
things outlined here so you said the hel
holtan the Helm Holt's decomposition is
of the flow is that if I'm looking at
the long Jaan equation that's not the
that doesn't include the random noise
that's just f ofx f yeah it's a de
composition of f ofx but also done in
relation to the noise term so is the
noise term so would that what I'm asking
here is when I'm splitting it into
solenoidal and gradient is that
splitting just the F ofx or the F ofx
and the
yeah Okay cool
so okay so there's a there's a
dissipative aspect in all of this so the
analogy that I thought of was um if you
create a Whirlpool let's say in your
sink or in a cup of coffee you get this
solenoidal flow right it's conservative
but due to I presume just friction you
get this dissipative uh ele this this
aspect where the swirling motion Fades
away yeah totally right let's is that is
that the gradient flow then sort of
infiltrating a purely solenoidal flow
yeah that's absolutely right another
example is if you put milk in your
coffee yeah there will be like the
standard
mixing uh of things which will be the
gradient flow then if should start
stirring the cup of coffee with a spoon
then you're adding C flow and is it
where they meet that Things become like
we can say things are dispa of because
for me philosophically dispa of means
that you had order and now you've got
less order but if you if everything
is if there's no solenoidal flows then
arguably there's no is there is there
any order to begin
with it's hard to say like I have
yeah I have trouble relating these
Notions to
order but I think there's like there's
like an indirect way of relating them
which is so Noto flow is always
something that circles around something
yeah you think about the Circadian
rhythm yeah us waking up and going to
sleep all these are Cycles they are
examples of sidal flow an aof flow has
um produces entropy so I think that's in
some sense related to order and disorder
if you want to maintain as a living
being if you want to maintain cidal flow
or just as a physical system you need to
be using energy and dissipating entropy
so that's kind of the
idea and that's just a consequence of
the mathematics and the physics yeah
yeah basically okay the fact that we
have senoidal flow within us like
rhythms and Cycles means that we need to
eat and uh and secrete right right okay
okay because in some sense the that's a
form of order which is neg
entropic yeah yeah okay now uh okay so
what is this um the other thing that
comes up is the term
Divergence right so people say that
solenoidal flows are zero
Divergent yeah what does that what does
that mean
right uh it's kind of that's just kind
of a mathematical term uh but uh because
if you take the Divergence of the vector
field it's zero but that's getting to
that I'll give you a picture if we if we
are at our steady state distribution so
let's say um our system is two
dimensional and it's distributed
according to gaussian that's sitting on
my table
here um the soal flow is uh motion
around the Contours of this gaussin
distribution and the gradient flow is
motion towards the peak or away from the
peak interesting and so we have our
overall motion which is given by the
flow in the Lan equation which could be
in any direction and then um the fact is
you can decompose it on motion towards
the peak so towards states are more
expected or preferred and motion away
from the peak strictly away from the
peak these two are Divergence free flow
you can also the other part of the
decomposition is motion that just goes
around the Contours of the distribution
which means that it does not approach
the peak or go away from the peak is it
if I'm thinking about it
diagrammatically does it matter where
that circulation is
going does it so so it could be at the
base of the gussan which means it would
in some like again just diagrammatically
means it would be wider or it could be
at the top of the Gan which means it's
occupying these high probability
states does it
matter um I think it matters as a
signature of the system probably I mean
this idea of Coto flow is one of the
most important like signatures of uh of
being alive and what your states are
doing what kind of Cycles you have in
your system or in yourself uh so it's a
very important um descriptor of what's
going on okay cool and the other thing
was um and again you can tell me when
I'm when I make a terrible fuxa is that
solenoidal flows break what's called
detailed balance yeah and what I've
learned about this is that detail
balance is when the rate of transitions
of any two states is equal in both
directions that's right so like you can
think of it in terms of I I I thought of
it in terms of like a crowd going in and
out of a
like a stadium or in and out of a room
that rate is going to be the same in and
out and that I believe and again you can
tell me if I'm wrong there's something
to do with boltzman boltzman's h
theorem which says that that that
detailed balance implies zero in that
entropy right um so so two parts um it's
absolutely right that detail balance is
means that there is flow
um in and out say of a stadium at at the
same rate it means that if you play the
flow in and out of the stadium forward
or backward it will look the same
there's no production of entropy and
there's no solal flow and the system is
time reversible yeah yeah yeah okay so
that kind of explains why the it's sort
of N Net Zero entropy right if entropy
is foundational to the passage of time
yeah yeah yeah basically yeah as soon as
you have S flow time uh starts taking
place you start having a narrow time
okay so if if we
took so yeah okay so this is interesting
so let let's let's kind of this is an
odd exercise but we can kind of build a
human from scratch right
so let's try right um so the the
gradient flows are going up or down the
probability distribution so we take a
human as just our gussian distribution
it's kind of going up down but let's say
it without any solenoidal flows we have
this detailed balance yeah so it's going
up and down
now does that not mean that because it's
doing it uh equally you're going to end
up at that
Peak uh no because you have equal flow
towards the peak or away from the peak
so how does that average out what does
that look like in terms of where I where
the crowd might be or they're just
everywhere
are we talking about the human or or the
crowd going in and out of let's say the
crowd let's say because we've got
detailed balance so let's say the crowd
okay okay if I'm gonna say okay uh I
have a random friend X and they're they
belong to this crowd that's uh behaving
in terms of detailed balance and I want
to find him is there a probability
distribution that could help
me to find your friend yes who's going
in you know is part of that TI
um yeah I'm not sure about that okay
what I will just say is that like if you
have one exit in your stadium with
people going in and out at the same rate
yeah and they're kind of like mixing
with each other so who is who you have
detail balance you just having one
entrance and one exit then you do not
have detail balance because you have
people coming in one way and going out
the other way so you start having a
cycle
ah okay now that's that's okay that's
really useful nice so let's now talk
about the human in a sense because the
hum a
combination of we're kind of what Carl
would say we're in this goldilock zone
so we're not orbital planets with just
solenoidal flows so we so we're not just
this cular uh circular thing but we're
also not just NE entrop non-- entropy
one it right so we have both so we have
both yeah so yeah it's a very
interesting sweet spot if you just
consider systems that have just the
gradient flow yeah are dead and you know
they might look like gases and stones
and stuff like that yeah yeah yeah if
you just look at things that has tornado
flow well I would say they're probably
dead as well it could be like like
planets orbiting around the Sun like
they're going One Direction and not the
other and we are kind of like in between
where we have both going on so I guess
this is where my question was going
which is okay let's say let's take a
Rock The Rock has uh just gradiant flows
so it's dead but it seems to me that the
rock is doing a pretty good job at self-
evidencing right
so does in some ways the solenoidal flow
take us away from Yes it gives us
animacy and whatever but does it take us
away from like just being being able to
rigidly self-evidence rigidly maximize
model evidence no um no no it does not
and so the beauty of the mathematics
here is that we're we're taking the most
General sort of equation that can
describe the world so the F principle
applies if there is C Noto flow and no
decied flow yeah it applies there is
decied flow and no solenoidal flow and
it applies if there's
both yes but what I mean by this is it's
it's probably worth mentioning that I'm
kind of thinking about this over time so
my uh my plastic bottle is going to
outlive me and and because things over
time have to you know have to abide by
the free energy principle they have to
look as if they're maximizing model
evidence or doing some variational Basi
and inference you could say if we had
some normative sense which again I'm
quite skeptical but you could say like
the water bottle is doing better
self-evidence over a period of time
uh yeah over over a long period of time
certainly and that's because well that
seems to me to map on quite nicely to
the
solenoidal gradient flow distinction
because like if rocks and uh I don't
know particles are not
solenoidal where where am I I feel like
I feel like there's something I'm
missing yeah that's uh I mean I think
it's very interesting you point out that
things
that do not have cidal flow sort of
endure over a longer period of time um I
never thought about that okay okay fine
fine fine fine I won't push it then okay
that's really okay yeah it's interesting
I need to think about it yeah yeah yeah
it well God don't know what kind of
worms I've just opened up I really don't
want to get shouted out on the comments
um okay so something I do understand a
little bit better is this uh KO
Divergence uh that's more up my streaks
I feel like it's a little bit more
cognitive sciencey so it's coolback Lio
Divergence and and as I said this Um
this can be cast as a distinction if
we're doing basian inference between a
true posterior and what's called the
recognition density um which is like
your version of your of of a posterior
now there was something you bought up in
that uh or car Bop or whoever wrote it
in that um simplifying the free energy
principle paper which is called a Fisher
information metric tensor which measures
changes in the K
Divergence it might be so people I think
view the variational for energy as a
kind of snapshot in time so given like
this perceptual inference how big is my
K Divergence given my action how much
surprise is there but this seems to me
to integrate change over time so what is
the Fisher information metric tensor and
how can we integrate that into a more
accurate or more faithful model of the
world or model of ourselves right uh
so once you accept that you have a
recognition density about the world and
that this is minimizing free energy you
can ask how much does your recognition
density or your beliefs about the world
have to change in order to minimize free
energy and so if you if you want to
quantify how much your beliefs move in a
certain amount of time you need what's
called uh an information metric
information metric in the sense that it
uh quantifies how much information
changes over time the information have
about and the information the fishal
information metric is what allows you to
do that nice okay cool are you are you
familiar with this notion that's been
coming out of maybe like the more
philosophical or cognitive science side
of active inference so people like Mark
Miller and Julian Kine of prediction
error
Dynamics um I mean intuitively I can see
what that would mean but yeah the idea
is that we have like a higher order
prior that we will track how good we're
doing at minimizing free energy over
time and this constitutes and and this
in terms of psychology maps onto
something like positive or negative
affect because you know we've got a
great we're doing well right we're doing
well we're finding these slopes of um
Vari variational for energy that we can
descend down and there kind of an
explanation for why we don't seek out
dark rooms so there's one other solution
to the dark room problem it sounds quite
similar to what you're saying which is
except what you're saying seems strictly
I I don't know in terms of the K
Divergence tied to perceptual inference
but we can say that a system is becoming
better perceptual inference because over
time those KO divergences are going
down is that reasonable to say well yes
and no because if if the data stream
sort of like stayed constant oh yes or
if you stop the data stream then your
kale Divergence would go down because
you would kind of like get a free energy
minimum yeah but always have new data
coming in so you have two forces at play
you have you uh who are like predicting
the data and minimizing free energy but
then you have data that's potentially
increasing the free energy right but is
the world but going back to our long
equation the world is the world is
modelable in some sense it's predictable
in certain senses so I I may be wrong
but it seems to me that the more data
you get over time the better your model
is going to be right it's it's just
going to become more powered right to
use a statistical
term what what's the kind of so that
seems to me that like your information
metric should be pointing that you know
your K divergencies are going down even
if you're getting more data because that
data's just it's got a similar
distribution to the data that came
before right okay so so I see I see
where where the confusion lies
um I agree with you that as we get more
dat data our model gets better and our
free energy um in general tends to be
lower so that's one truth the other
truth is that even though even even
though I mean that's a fact your the
data that's coming in keeps
changing uh which means that the
posterior density the true the true
keeps changing so your recognition
Dynamics always have to keep tracking
this posterior distribution right now
the fish looks at how much these um
recognition Dynamics have to travel in a
certain period of time to match the true
posterior is there an equation that
governs that because obviously I've
become obsessed with equations um is
there is there how much your beliefs
change no not just how much your beliefs
change but kind of how the data
changes how the data changes that's the
longine equation long equation but it's
so that's the function of the X being
the worldly States
yeah got it got it okay okay yes okay I
see where my confusion was I guess I was
viewing the world
as kind of static I mean you can even
like take away the r the the random
noise right if your f ofx is changing
your agent who's modeling that is going
to have to keep updating keep changing
their model nice nice okay cool that's
that's that's very useful okay excellent
um okay have I got any more maths um I
got a bit more maths I guess one one
something I wanted to ask about is this
is a broader question so in so in active
inference we have discrete State spaces
and continuous State spaces so and it's
kind of about the how we carve up time
in some sense so continuous State spaces
is where it doesn't really make sense to
put time into separate chunks or
sequential chunks so you know if you're
thinking about attention or perception
or perception let's say um I know
perception includes some action but
let's just take perception it's better
to kind of model that in terms of a
continuous State space if you're
thinking about decision- making you
would think about that in terms of
discret State spaces because an action
policy is a discrete thing in discret
state space we've seen this kind of
proliferation of So-Cal pom DP schema um
so these are these partially observable
Markov decision blank but process close
always think about Marco blankets um is
there an equival
of that in continuous State
spaces uh so you can definitely have
continuous uh parti obser Mark of
decision
processes um so so let let me take a
step back there's two things that play
there's a whether the stage space is
discrete or continuous and whether time
is discrete or continuous okay now in
active inference implementation so far
you basically have either continuous
space continuous time or discret space
discret time yeah yeah or both but
people haven't really been playing with
continuous space discrete time right uh
continuous time discrete
space but there's no reason why in
principle you you would not be able to
do that okay that's cool well uh this is
again my very much lay and knowledge of
physics um do we not take time and space
to be somewhat
interwoven
um yeah this is a bit beyond me I guess
I guess I guess a way around this is to
say that we're modeling right so in our
modeling we can take time as continuous
and space as discret and vice versa yeah
this is this is only about modeling
about how you represent the world but
there is a a deep uh a deeper question
which is how do we ultimately like
represent the world in physics and it's
true that some theories you know
consider time and space jointly but for
us humans uh yeah we don't need to get
into that for active res modeling okay
so we we've we've kind of clarified that
so when so where would the pomdp schemes
be able to be used if it's not just
discrete time discrete space they
applicable to continuous space
continuous
time so so where would you actually use
them so I've seen for example just to
give some background I've kind of seen
pom DP schemes used in mainly just
aspect like context of decision
making so um for example yeah going back
to the flow paper flow involves
selecting action policies meditation
involves mental action um attention
right like um
intentional uh attention uh endogenous
attention is a
decision these can all be modeled quite
nicely but to my eyes everyone who talks
about perception will use something like
a predictive coding scheme yeah um is
there is that I'm just curious about
what is if there is an alternative to
that in the
literature in the literature no okay I
was talking to Ryan Smith recently and
he was interested in continuous State P
DP with
discret and so the idea here is that you
can Model A continuous representation of
the world and a sequential decision
making at the same time of that
so possibilities okay cool I'm speaking
to Ryan fairly soonish so that that
would be useful that would be cool
that's a good thing to bring up yeah
that's really interesting I don't know
this brings to mind there's this
incredible paper by a guy called Juan
Diego botar and I think his name is
Zacharia
Jabara and it's sort of symphasis
subjective time and objective time
through a basian model and I'm going to
tell you I stared to that graph for
about 6
hours um and it still did make sense so
that's a you know if anyone wants to
read that and try and think about how
maybe not space and time but like two
different types of time can be coals
that's a good place to start so I I'll
give you another theory of mine uh I
attended this wonderful work workshop on
computational neurop
phenomenology uh last year and I had a
wonderful conversation with annel Seth
and we kind of converged onto the
hypothesis that subjective time is uh
the amount of distance that your beliefs
travel over some period of objective
time okay cool so here here's the thing
like when you when your beliefs move a
lot yeah and you can quantify that with
the Fisher information metric you would
have a perception that a lot of time has
elapsed okay so you've now got me on
this new pet hobby of mine because
I'm sure you haven't seen it but
literally yesterday I published a
preprint called distrusting the policy
how inference over action shapes our
perception of
time that's cool I should read so so
please I would love some feedback
basically I wrote it so and this this
started off as being trying to explain
temporality in flow States and I thought
no actually this works I think this
works more
broadly so I'm not going to spoil it
well I will spoil it but basically my
idea so I'm building off what yakob
Harry called distrusting the present so
this is very similar to what you're
saying so yakob Harry has this idea that
this the flow of time is contingent on
um the rate at which we update our
perceptual hypothesis about the world so
if I'm in a volatile environment I the
uh the state estimation I have at time T
is not going to work for t plus one and
so what happens is the moment I find T I
immediately start discounting it which
you can consider sort of precision
waiting and immediately I have to update
that and he C that now I I don't think
that that totally maps onto the
phenomenology because I'm really curious
about what you think about this and
again I will try and do it quickly
because I don't want to bore you but we
have
um so I say so he was kind of it seems
to me he was rooting uh flow of time in
predictability but the problem is is if
you're going to cast it only in terms of
perception or only in terms of the a
matrix then you you've got a slight
problem because there are two different
types of predictability you've got one
which I call static predictability which
is basically when you're staring at a
wall now when you're staring at a wall
your perceptual hypothesis is going to
be pretty good let's say over a prolong
period of time and so Jacob's Theory
says time will slow down and it does
right you stare at a wall for an hour
it's going to feel like a day yeah but
then the other problem is something
called Dynam what I call Dynamic
predictability so let's say you've
played a video game level once it's very
exciting time seems to flow quickly now
let's say I make you play that same
video game a 100
times now perceptually the world is
changing you got to do all of that state
like that state estimation that
combination of the D Matrix and the a
matrix needs to keep happening at the
same rate and I want to flesh this out
experimentally but I have a hunch that
time is going to move way
slower
so what I've what I've now said is it's
about the frequency with which you
update your action policies and the
reason why I said that is because with
each action policy updating you also
have to update your beliefs in the C
Matrix and the C Matrix is your expected
pre uh your preferred sensory
observations and that I think accounts
for the perceptual aspect of the flow of
time that's really that's a really
interesting hypothesis yeah yeah so I so
it's Friday the 19th of January on
Tuesday people are not going to be able
to you know this is not people can't go
back in time anyway I'm doing a talk
about it at the at the institute on
Tuesday um so anyway that that's so I
think we're converging on similar points
here I think it's kind of where is the
source of your information change so for
me it's the C Matrix really because it
can't be the B Matrix because in Dynamic
predictable so uh B Matrix of State
transitions in dynamically predictable
situations like playing the same video
game 100 times I'm going to have the
same number of B
matrices compared to when I played it
the first time so I don't think it's the
B Matrix but because I you have to keep
doing this expected free energy
calculation for each action policy and
the C Matrix feeds into that my hunch is
that it might be rooted than that right
you you could also think about the fact
that if you replay the video game uh
like many times mhm your belief still
have to move to adapt to the current uh
situation in the video game but there
will be less and less novelty yeah
because you adapted your like big world
model to like predict the video game
very so how that translates to in
practice is that you have lowlevel
beliefs that that move a lot to you
adapt to current situation but high
level beliefs that don't move because
okay nice everything again I think I'm
trying to get this to be done
experimentally to
see if it's if if this Theory maps onto
anything yeah it would be really nice to
test but that's that's a very
interesting yeah I'm always in favor of
all all of the empirical
experiments I feel as a community we
we're lacking that I think that's right
and I think it shouldn't be that hard to
do I think you just have to give people
statically predictable context
dynamically predictable context and flow
context yeah I
mean um as soon as you can map a p onto
the data that's coming in be very easy
to model everything that's going on well
I may reach out to you or LS on that one
um Okay cool so that that was a fun
little for um okay actually let's let's
um we we spoke we very briefly touched
upon
attention um and I have a question about
attention if I may i' I've been I've
been I've been grappling with attention
for quite a long time um so attention is
kind of construed as optimization of the
likelihood distribution in active
inference of the a matrix in the pomdp
schema
now there are these really lovely papers
by his name is mitah so uh mital 2016
2018 and 2019 I think and he shows he
gives this example of like searching for
a red pen and he says that when you're
searching for a red pen what you do is
you downweight sensory Precision of
stimuli that are Rel irrelevant to that
context and so basically you end up
doing Salient Behavior which is we can
view as epistemically Salient because it
yields Information Gain but the
information that you
want um now given that um yeah so that
makes sense because task relevant
stimuli are downweighted so only task
relevant stimul involved in this maximal
Information Gain okay fine but
pragmatically so so that epis that
information gain is like I didn't know
where the red pen was now I know where
the red pen is yeah but in terms of
pragmatic in terms of pragmatics we know
that action policies in uh Act of
influence are driven by a kind of almost
a false belief a false preference so I
might say I have a red pen and I'm going
to go out there to confirm that belief
because without it there's lots of
prediction error or variation or free
energy this seems to be a kind of issue
because on one hand I'm gaining
information about the world so I kind of
knew that I didn't have a pen and now I
know where the pen is and so my I have
this K Divergence but then I also have
this oddly pragmatic belief that I do
have a red pen because without that red
without that belief I wouldn't be
motivated to go and get the red pen so
I'm I'm trying to Grapple with how to
resolve that clash and I'm curious if
you can
help yeah not sure um but what I'm
thinking is uh I always think about
attention as control of the a Matrix so
kind of like in large large's paper on
meditation mhm uh you make some some uh
sensory modalities more
precise and others less precise yeah and
it feeds into into your
computations yes
so yeah see I've always I've always
found it quite useful to distinguish
Precision from Precision waiting so
Precision I just view as the kind of
inverse entropy or of a
distribution but Precision waiting is
actually what I do right I wait
precision and that's not all going to be
down weirdly Precision waiting is not
all down to
Precision well isn't it I think it often
is it often is in terms of so they talk
about how attention is basically one
definition of it is the capacity to kind
of sift through the data that you
currently have for the most uh
informationally reliable or precise um
data right so the one that's going to
say okay given this I know exactly what
caused it but
clearly like for example in my searching
of the red pen there's going to be loads
of things in the environment that are
that have a very uh you know very strict
uh relationship mapping between the
observation and the state so while I'm
scanning I might see something and go oh
obviously that's my phone right it's not
ambiguous whether it's my phone or not
but because I'm but the whole point of
this Mit paper is I don't I don't care
so I'm downweighting that stimuli but
that's nothing to do with how well it
maps onto some
State yeah
yeah it isn't okay so if I understand
correctly this is um because you you
want to conform to your prior
belief and therefore if your prior
belief is very precise mhm uh you will
discount whatever sensory information
comes in right so my prior belief is
yeah so my prior belief is something
like I have a red
pen and and and so that's very precise
and yeah so that leads you to Discount
things that are because you're
you're you're yeah you're only going to
pay attention to things that are task
relevant yeah then so but that but
that's kind of but the point is that's
kind of a belief saying I have a pen but
then there still is this epistemic gain
which is at the heart of Sal
which is I didn't have a pen or I didn't
know where the pen was and now I do know
where the pen is and so you're starting
with I don't know where the pen is but
for your act to Trigger action you have
the belief I know where the pen
is to to Trigger action to look for the
pen I'm I'm getting I'm getting a little
bit lost okay so so um preferences
underly action right so a see Matrix so
I have the preference about the sensory
information that I expect to receive mhm
so let's say and and preferences can be
casted as just beliefs so I believe so
for example uh in some very it's it's
some very subpersonal way I believe that
uh I'm going to be at 37.9 degrees and
so I act so I remain around that now I
want to find my red pen we can cast that
valtion as a preference as a belief yeah
I know where my red pen is and the
reason why you would do that is because
well the world is not giving you that
information and so you've got prediction
error and you want to minimize that
prediction error so that triggers action
to confirm the belief that you have a
red
pen okay that's on one side but on the
other
side what captures attention is that
which is most Salient and what salience
can be cast as is epistemic gain
Information
Gain and that for me in this red pen
example looks like well I didn't know
where the red pen was and now I do know
where the red pen is
but what you've got on one hand is on
the epistemic side you've start with the
belief I don't know where the pen is
because if I did know where the pen is
finding the pen would not be very useful
right so that's um inhibition of return
that kind of explains inhibition of
return that's on the epistemic side on
the pragmatic side I have I have a
pen so I'm just asking how those two
things come
together I'm I'm so sorry Darius I think
my brain is fried by that's all right
that's right I'm sure someone in the
comments will have an answer yeah I kind
of feel feel that KL will just have an
answer um I mean I'm sure I'm sure he
has an answer to everything Maybe not
maybe not okay let's um a research paper
yeah maybe I I know that one's going to
take me down some wormholes
um so okay last thing I guess I want to
talk about is you went on the machine
learning Street Talk podcast and you
spoke a lot about core knowledge which I
thought was really interesting I really
didn't expect that to come up um but I
know it's one of your interest
terms of what are the kind of priors
that need that are uilt that
facilitate intelligence sentient
Behavior
so I guess what are your current
thoughts on how so it's interesting
because I actually come from a
Linguistics background as I told you
before we started and at least you know
at Oxford where I was they they love
Chomsky so Chomsky has this notion of
universal grammar there's something
built into the genetic code that
facilitates language learning so I'm
very familiar with these arguments
Poverty of stimulus and these arguments
in terms of antism nativism what are
your thoughts on how fleshed out those
priors are um in terms of being
innate well I think there's definitely
innate priors when we were born and this
is all studied um I think one of the
best people is Elizabeth shelki y her
whole career uh describing and
characterizing those priors MH uh these
seem to be incredibly
precise uh much like we cannot change
them and they seem to be super General
in the sense that they would apply to
any kind of naturalistic or physical
environment that you could ever be bored
in so these are things like object
permanence two object cannot uh interact
at a distance but two people can
interact at a distance so so two agents
can uh I think there's a core knowledge
system for um numbers learning numbers
there might also be a core knowledge
system for
language uh they might also be one for
vision uh so there's six of them and she
wrote a book about it uh which is what
babies know uh that I absolutely
recommend with with all of that research
so it's a big research program to
actually being able to understand those
and reveal those coronal systems it's
another one to be able to reverse
engineer them
interesting yeah I think one of the
issues I guess is at least um in the
history of linguistics one of the great
problems was how rich are these priors
so this is what later got known as
Darwin's problem uh because tumpsky has
this idea that well in the 80s he had
this principles and parameters idea
which is that what ug is is a bunch of
parameters that can be switched on on uh
you know given sensory data those
parameters get switched on or off and
then the problem is you had this massive
proliferation of parameters so there
were 500 parameters and Fin and finished
people you know there was one only for
finish but obviously we all had it but
only unless you were exposed to finish
did you ever turn it on and it just
became completely inexplicable given
Evolution because how on Earth did one
mutation or a couple of mutations
trigger that so he now thinks that
there's something a lot more paired down
something like recursion and I think why
why that's interesting is because
recursion is not is not what we call
propositional Knowledge it's not
knowledge that something so Trump might
say oh okay you know in the 60s might
said okay I know the baby knows that
after this comes this or something but
now this is just actually a mechanism so
what we might call procedural knowledge
when you think about uh core knowledge
for maths or call knowledge for vision
or I guess Vision really won't be
propositional call knowledge for
language
are you construing these as
propositional or
procedural um
so well these would be priories in the G
of
model which could be
expressed um in a number of ways it
could be uh sort of like um like a
grammar of uh like core components that
you already have in your G model well
well let let me put it in a different
way like when we're born we have a very
simple gen model and gradually we learn
about the RO around this and we make it
more complex now what we have at the
beginning is is this core knowledge it's
kind of like a starting point Gant model
that allows you to right by structure
learning learn about everything else now
the structure of that is uh very debated
among computational people so for
example Josh tenenbom is pursuing this
idea of probabilistic
programs which are B based on symbolic
grammars and probabilistic rules between
different
entities then there's other people who
might uh model these things with neural
networks right so in those cases you
don't have symbols you don't have that
grammar going on yeah it's very much an
open area of research cool yeah I mean I
guess all these neural networks still
have some priors
um in in a lot of cases yeah awesome
yeah yeah I used to love these debates
between Chomsky and people like um
Jeffrey Elman sort of mid
1990s proper hardcore stuff cool and
yeah I I it's interesting you mention
Vision because I always thought that for
me the one glaring one where there needs
to be PRI is Vision vision is perception
is well visual perception is such an
amazing
capacity yeah to be able to there is a
startup called a Common Sense machines
MH has pushed the core knowledge of
vision really to state-of-the-art level
where they have a world model for vision
and then they do inference on that world
model and they they're able to
reconstruct 3D scenes from 2D images wow
in in a pretty amazing way so yeah out
have you seen these things uh the this
is slightly different but you have these
neuron Nets that are trained on like uh
brain Imaging data
and they can take an MRI of the brain
and say that this person was thinking
about a dolphin or something they can
have an image of what that person is
thinking about obviously we're given the
training that you know there is this I'm
not going to say causation correlation I
won't go into it but that you know when
this part when this brain data is like
this this person is thinking this and so
you have the testimonies of the people
but it just shows the power of those and
the and the kind of nuance of those
large language models that they can be
able to do that um but but actually I
think it's arguably less exciting than
people think it is because they forget
about the training process that
underlies it yeah and it doesn't allow
you to understand it just allows you to
predict exactly exactly and that's where
that's where our our favorite topic of
active inference might might come in
maybe and yield some artificial
understanding hopefully hope well people
are getting very excited getting very
excited L that was that was awesome I
feel like I've leared I feel like I've
gone to University again yeah me too
no this no this was this was so much fun
I knew it would be fun thank you for
being gentle with me and kind with the
maths well thanks for having me no it
was an absolute pleasure um I really
want to see what comes out of this stuff
especially with annel about the Fisher
information metric and time yeah is g to
come out really cool yeah cool sounds
like we're converging potentially on a
similar idea so yeah it would be really
nice to talk I need to flesh out these
ideas and then yeah we can talk more
Splendid okay well thank you from longan
and [ __ ] PL and all of this stuff it's
been an absolute pleasure so thank you
for myself and The Institute it's been a
great pleasure for me too thanks